They have a serious problem with
espionage in their country. Yes.
>> Why? Why so Why is it so
>> Well,
>> prolific?
>> I I have to keep reminding myself that
cuz I'm on the side of the Iranians in
this whole thing. But I have to keep my
reminding myself that Iran has big
problems, too. They're perfectly happy
to hang you from a crane by your neck if
you say something that the government
doesn't like. Okay, it's not all milk
and honey over there.
>> [cough and clears throat]
>> Excuse me. They have serious problems.
And so, um,
and so this isn't a government that
engenders such goodwill that it can
go out and do anything it wants.
>> I see.
>> With that said then, there are people in
the country
who hate their government and are
willing to work against it, risking
death.
And they already, a week ago, they
already started executing people
just suspected
of working for the uh
for the Syrians. Now, you know, I mean I
mean for the Israelis. One of the things
that the Israelis did last week that was
just
that was a surprise to me, but was very
effective technique and something that
the US did to the Iraqis in 2003
is
you start calling people and threatening
them. Right? There was a fantastic
>> What's
>> reporting in the Washington Post of a
Mossad uh a Farsi-speaking Mossad
officer calling a an Iranian general and
saying, "Look, we're going to kill you
tomorrow."
And then we know that they did this to a
number of generals. They First they they
slipped notes under their apartment
doors in the middle of the night saying,
"Hey, we're going to kill you tomorrow."
This is your only chance. You can come
work for us or we're going to kill you
tomorrow. Then they called their wives
and said, "We're going to kill your
husband tomorrow and we may take down
the entire apartment building, so tell
him to get on the right side of this."
And then finally they called the
generals themselves, which is what you
heard on that Washington Post um
recording saying, "We're going to kill
you
unless you make a video
renouncing support for the Iranian
government and announcing support for
the Israeli government.
Now, that that's obviously a death
sentence to do something like that. Why
would you do something like that? But
then they
legitimately went out and killed every
one of these guys,
more than a half a dozen of them.
So, they've got their cell phones, they
have their addresses, they can track
their movements. And one of the things
about the Israelis, too, and we saw this
in spades in in Beirut and in southern
Lebanon, is if somebody is in an
apartment building, somebody who's a
target is in an apartment building, they
will take down the entire block
if they can be sure that they're killing
this one person. They'll kill hundreds
just to get that one person.
That's why the death toll was so much
higher.
>> I guess that brings two questions. For
one, why didn't Iran reciprocate?
And two,
how
And let me ask first the second one
first. How do they go about recruiting
spies? I mean, I would imagine there
would be some of Saudi agent
>> [clears throat]
>> who would try to get close to somebody,
"Hey, I'll give you money. I'll give
you" cuz they ended up having a lot of
Afghans and a lot of Indians.
And correct me if I'm wrong on this,
that they found were working with the
Israelis. Not to mention, you know,
groups like MEK or whatever.
>> Right. They were in
>> Yeah. This is mostly refugees. This this
intelligence network that they have
inside Iran. You know, the conventional
wisdom
Jabar is that the Israelis recruit
Iranian Jews. There are more Jews in
Iran
than any other country. I'm sorry. Yeah,
that's right. There there more Jews in
Iran than any other country in the
Middle East outside of Israel.
>> Wow.
>> And so the conventional wisdom is oh,
they just recruit these Iranian Jews.
Not true. Iranian Jews are loyal to the
Iranian government.
In fact, many of them volunteered
for the military just to fight the
Israelis.
But Iran has struggled for decades
with a refugee crisis.
Millions, literally millions of Afghans
and Pakistani Baloch have crossed into
Iran since 1979.
They're not eligible for Iranian
citizenship. They're not eligible for
Iranian government aid because they're
not Iranians.
And so if you are desperate and hungry
and have no alternative,
that is a vulnerability that the Mossad
has been able to exploit.
So if you're if you're some penniless
refugee from Afghanistan
in Tehran
and they give you the Israelis give you
$500 and say get me the addresses of
these five generals or 10 or 20
generals, by God, you're going to do it
and you're going to transmit it back to
them.
>> How do these refugees get into the
country in general? I mean, this may be
a stupid question
>> No,
that's a good question. The border is
absolutely
massive and it's unprotected. It's just
too big and it's too rough and it's too
mountainous. And I'll give you an idea
of this.
In 2009 when I joined the staff of the
Senate Foreign Relations Committee,
John Kerry, who was the chairman at the
time,
told me that he wanted to reach out to
the Iranians.
>> Mhm.
>> So I sent a letter
under his signature to the Iranian
ambassador to the United Nations and I
said
we wanted to meet.
So, I went up to New York and I met with
the Iranian ambassador secretly.
And I said Senator Kerry is interested
in improving relations with Iran. This
is before the JCPOA was even proposed.
>> Yeah.
>> Kerry was really gung-ho about trying to
make things right with the Iranians.
And the Iranians said
"That sounds great. We want weapons. We
want night vision goggles. We want
secure communications with encryption.
We want ammunition." And I was like,
"No, no, no, no, no, no, no. That's not
what I'm I'm not here to talk about
that."
>> Right. [laughter]
Right.
>> Money, guns, lawyers.
>> It's It's because they simply can't
control the border. And remember,
this is how all that Afghan heroin gets
into Iran, too. The border is just so
big and so rough and so mountainous,
they just can't control it.
>> Interesting.
Oh, that's so interesting.
I guess to bounce back to the other
question, why don't they reciprocate? I
mean, Israel had no issue murdering
civilians. They didn't have no issue
taking down apartment buildings. Why
does Iran hold itself to some weird
standard when they're dealing with
monsters that don't have those
standards?
>> That is a very good question. And as as
background, I'm going to say
notice
the difference in the death tolls in the
two countries, right? Four, five, six
times
the number of people in Iran were killed
than were killed in uh Israel. Not
because the Iron Dome protected them.
But the Iranians legitimately attacked
military and economic targets. Of
course, there were a couple of errant
missiles that that hit, you know,
apartment buildings, but the Israelis
actively
target civilian
residential areas.
They want that big death toll. They want
to kill that one general even if it
means killing 200 other people in the
building. And the Iranians didn't do
that. They They took the high road.
And that was a policy decision they
made. I'm not sure why they did. I think
they did it to be on the right side of
international law, frankly.
>> Mhm.
>> Um
one of the things that the Iranians have
have
shown the rest of us
in two go-rounds now with the Israelis
is that the Iron Dome isn't so vaunted
as it's been cracked up to be.
You know, if those slow-motion drones
can get through, and remember in the
first go-round, seven drones got
through, right? Seven. That's a lot.
That tells me that that the Iron Dome
doesn't really work like they say it
works. And then enough missiles got
through
to actually do damage.
Iran is a gigantic country. It has 92
million people. And just in terms of
area, it's massive. And what does Israel
have? 8 million, I guess.
>> 8 million. Yeah.
>> Yeah.
>> So, Iran can, you know, take a licking
and keep on ticking as the old Timex
commercial used to used to say.
>> Oh, your point is Oh, I'm sorry. I
thought you were still going. Your your
point is effectively they willingly
absorb, knowing full Yeah, I guess it's
the argument I used to make, too, that
if it's pound for pound, even if Israel
can dish out three times more, Israel's
going to get crushed. It can't.
>> get crushed? The Israelis The Israelis
would have to use nuclear weapons. And
to do that would be I think it would be
the end of Israel.
>> Why do you think it'll be the end of
Israel?
>> Because the West
with the United States aside cuz we're,
you know, beholden to the Israelis,
I think the West would walk away from
Israel if they used nuclear weapons.
Without having nuclear weapons used on
them.
>> But now
but see this is the part that that gets
me and that goes this is where
my main disagreement goes with this.
Intellectually,
I would hope that to be true.
But by the same token I never thought
I'd watch a genocide take place in real
time.
Like meaning I never thought I'd watch
kids walking around like skeletons.
That is mind-blowing. I've never seen
that. Nor would I did I think I would
ever see that.
>> Have you ever been
like to the West Bank or Gaza?
>> Yeah, Bethlehem.
>> That's a Christian that's a Christian
town. Have you been like to Nablus,
let's say, or
>> Mhm. No.
>> Tomorrow it is
it's like walking from the
from the first world into the into the
fourth world.
It's the biggest prison
on Earth. The biggest open-air prison on
Earth.
You know,
my mom said to me one time in 2008, my
dad had died and she wanted to travel.
So she called me one day and she said,
"I think I'm going to go to Ireland with
your sister." And I said, "Ireland?" I
said, "What do you want to go to Ireland
for in February?" You know how cold and
rainy it is in Ireland? I said, "The
priest at my church is taking a a group
to Israel, Mom. You should go to
Israel." And she's like, "Oh, that's a
great idea." So she and my sister went.
My mom had zero
political perspective. Didn't know
anything.
Wasn't really interested in politics or
foreign affairs. She came back
as a 100%
Palestine activist. She said to me, she
was so sweet about it. She said,
"Did you have any idea how those
Israelis treat the Palestinians?"
And I said, "Of course, like my whole
adult life
I've been watching the way they treat
the Palestinians." And she said, she
cried a couple of times.
She cried at a roadblock one time. They
had a Palestinian
Christian, Greek Orthodox, driver for
their little, you know, their little van
that that held 12 people.
>> This happened to me, too. You go play.
>> And she said, "The guy was a
professional driver, and he would drive
them to Bethlehem, and drive them to
Nazareth, and just sit in the van. So,
they come to an IDF roadblock, and the
guy's reading some
some pulp fiction, you know, novel while
everybody's inside the church taking
pictures. And an IDF soldier grabbed the
book out of his hand, and opened it up
and said,
"No picture of Arafat on this page." And
tore out the page, and threw it at him.
he tore out clumps of pages out, and
threw it at him. And the poor driver
just sat there and took it.
>> Yeah.
>> And she said to him,
"Why do you allow them to treat you like
that?" And he said, "Madam, the
alternative is that they shoot me."
>> Yeah.
>> And then she said, "As if that wasn't
bad enough, as they're entering the West
Bank, there are these 30-ft walls with
barbed wire on the side,
um or on the top, rather,
that the Israelis said were to keep the
Palestinians out of Israel." And she
said, "They're not. They're to keep the
Palestinians, or sorry, to keep the
Palestinians in
Palestine, in cages. It's a prison." And
I said, "Kalimera." It's something the
Greeks say, "Good morning." Like you
just woke up and realized that this is
the reality in in Palestine, or occupied
Palestine, which is what the West Bank
is. So, I think part of our problem here
in the United States is most Americans
either don't know that
or refuse to acknowledge it. You know, I
taught years ago at Liberty University,
an evangelical university. I'm not
evangelical. I have nothing in common
with them, but they offered me a
teaching position and I accepted it. I'm
for whatever reason I'm still on the
listserv of professors. And I mean, I
taught there in 2011.
>> Yeah.
>> Um 2010, 2011.
So, I'm still on the listserv.
And the the the ugly vociferous
hatred that I see for Palestinians on
this listserv is disguised as
support for Israel
and opposition to terrorism.
Well, none of these people have ever met
a Palestinian. None of these people have
ever been to Palestine or to Israel.
They're just going by what they see on
Fox and the One America Network and what
they hear, you know, in their
Bible-beating
uh evangelical churches.
So, a lot of this is a result in the
United States as a result of ignorance,
in many cases willful ignorance.
And I think that as things continue to
get worse
and our European allies become more
vocal
in their opposition to what we're seeing
today, starving literally starving
children,
I think they're going to begin to drag
Americans with them in that direction.
>> Mark, I I mean, I'm sorry, not Mark, um
John, I
I don't I I got to be honest, I don't
see it.
I you know, stuff like this is just
everyday now.
This is daily. Just children as
skeletons.
>> Yes.
>> And you see like when I was in Bethlehem
it was never that bad like
>> Oh, no, no, no, never.
>> I remember they pulled my van driver out
because apparently he didn't have some
kind of identification took the man to
jail somewhere. And in perfect English
Hey, um another driver will come in a
moment to take you to wherever you're
going. And you know, it's like you see
that stuff like you when you I remember
when we got into LA LA looks like little
America.
And then when you cross into Bethlehem
you're
>> it is.
>> Yeah, it just two different
>> Different different country. Yes.
>> bizarre.
>> Yes.
>> And you know, you get back to the states
my ex-wife I remember the first time she
went to Israel with me and she didn't
understand why I was
being a bit of a dick, right? Cuz for
one I didn't want to be there at that
point.
>> [snorts]
>> What year was this?
>> This was maybe four or five years ago.
>> Recently. Mhm.
>> This was recent.
She didn't she didn't get it cuz she's
not really political in that sense.
And I remember when we were leaving and
she says, you know, I was at the museum
she says it dawned on me
if Israel if all these Israelis came
here, who was here for you know, when
they got here?
And she's like it kind of dawned on her
like, oh, that's why all of these people
are in van in these places with guns.
That's why they were running around with
all of the military. That's why. Meaning
it took her a while to click of
who was here before these people got
here.
It it's just it's just it is a wild it
is an alternate reality. It it's truly
>> And Americans have no idea. The last
time I was there, I was in Jerusalem.
This is 2022.
I was actually there to cover the
Israeli elections for Sputnik.
>> Yeah.
>> And
>> I remember this. I remember them sending
you I'm sorry. I remember them sending
you
>> There were two two things. One, I would
see these signs everywhere. Billboards,
banners, we are with you, America.
I'm like,
on what? You're with us on what? We
don't want to be with you. Like, what
are these stupid billboards? That was
the first thing. The second thing,
it was my last full day in Israel and I
had to do
Actually, I had to do your show.
Um you were early in the morning.
>> Yeah.
>> Was it 7:00 to 10:00, I think?
Eastern. Okay, so so Israel was 7 7
hours ahead and I was going to be on at
8:00. So, I had the day free until 3:00
p.m.
until I had to get on your show.
And I hadn't yet gone to the Mount of
Olives and I wanted to see the Garden of
Gethsemane and the Virgin Mary's uh
you know, tomb stuff like that.
So, I went in the morning
and I I went to the Mount of Olives and
then I thought, okay, I'm I'm going to
go back into the Old City of Jerusalem
and buy a souvenir.
So, I'm on the Mount of Olives, you go
down into the valley and then back up to
get to the Old City. And to tell you the
truth, I was 115 lb heavier at the time.
And it was freaking hot that day. So,
when I get back up
to the Old City, I'm winded.
So, I sat on a bench
like 20 ft outside the iron gate, which
is one of the gates of the Old City.
>> Mhm.
>> And there's a woman sitting there and
she says, "Hi." And I said, "Hi."
And she asked me where I was from and I
said, "DC. Where are you from?" "Oh, I'm
from Brooklyn. Isn't this city amazing?"
"Yeah, it's amazing, but I can't believe
how they treat the Palestinians."
Etcetera. So, we're just sitting there
chatting.
And
as I'm talking to her, I'm watching,
again, from 20 ft away,
I'm watching the actual entrance to the
I'm at the iron gate, which isn't iron,
it's stone, but anyway.
Um
there were three IDF soldiers standing
in the iron gate, and they're just
standing there, milling around, and it's
this hustle and bustle of Palestinians
holding, you know, crates of
fruits and vegetables, dates, and
they're they're going about their day,
trading, buying, selling.
There's this one Palestinian guy who's
kind of milling around.
One of the IDF soldiers
went over, he was about 10 ft away, went
over to ask him, "What are you doing?"
And as the soldier went over there,
he pulls out a knife and he stabs the
guy twice. He stabs the soldier twice in
the stomach, right underneath the the
bulletproof vest that he was wearing.
Immediately, one of the other soldiers
put up his gun and shot him and killed
him.
Right there in front of my eyes.
This woman I'm with screams, and I said,
"We better get the hell out of here, cuz
they're going to lock it down." I took
off.
I was directly across the sidewalk, the
walkway from the back entrance to the
the um
the Rockefeller [snorts]
Archaeological Museum. So, I ran that
way, came out on the other side, went to
my hotel, and called Sputnik.
And she ran the other way back to the
Mount of Olives. They locked down the
entire Old City of Jerusalem.
And if I hadn't been able to run like
that,
I would have been caught up in all that
hell.
I mean, within minutes,
helicopters flying around, everything's
locked down,
armored personnel carriers entering the
old city. It was
it was awful.
And then,
I put on the Israeli news, the English
language Israeli news, just to see what
they were saying about this.
And it was
"They hate us more than they love life
itself.
It is only by the grace of God that our
man wasn't killed. You can see that they
have only murder in their hearts." It's
like, are you [__] kidding me?
>> It's like they don't see it.
>> They just don't see it.
>> It's the most bizarre thing. I remember
I was having a conversation I was
interviewing I guess it was a debate
with Benjamin Netanyahu's press guy
once.
And it to me, the most rational thing in
the world is, do you understand that
because [clears throat] of the way you
treat them, you're creating your
monsters?
>> They don't get it.
>> Completely over their head.
Completely over their head. It it it's
just
>> You know, I I gave a I gave a talk to um
to the Canadian Foreign Ministry on
Thursday last week. Big big thing. I had
125 people show up for the Zoom call.
And um one of the very first questions
they asked me was, how do we get out of
this
this constant cycle of terrorism and
war?
And I said, you know, this was one of
the very first lessons that I learned
when I was the the head of
counterterrorism operations in Pakistan
for the CIA.
I said, we started capturing Al-Qaeda
fighters
immediately. As soon as I arrived, we
would just bust down the door and
>> Give us those two shows, John.
>> Uh Deep Program. That's along with Ted
Rall. And the other is called Deep Focus
with John Kiriakou.
>> Deep Focus. John, thank you for this,
man. I I appreciate it.
>> Thank you, buddy.
>> Good to see you.
>> okay.
Have a good one.
All right.